Guide to the Steel Process Lantern Slide Collection, ca. 1907-1927 AIS.2014.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Steel Process Lantern Slide Collection
ca. 1907-1927
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Colonial Steel Company
AIS.2014.01
80 items (2 boxes)
This collection of 80 lantern slides documents steel mills, the steelmaking process, and railroad activities during the early 20th century, specifically the Colonial Steel Company.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Kenneth Kobus in 2014.
Scope and Content Notes
The Steel Process Lantern Slide Collection contains 80 lantern slides organized into three series documenting steel mills, the steelmaking process, and railroad activities during the early 20th Century. The Colonial Steel Company is represented in 24 slides with 53 slides depicting the steel making process from various mills in Pennsylvania and New York. The remaining three slides are topical and depict railroads and a gardening program at a Philadelphia school.
Arrangement
Series I. Colonial Steel Company, c.1917-1927
Series II. Steel Processes, Products, and Equipment
Series III. Topical
Previous Citation
Steel Process Lantern Slide Collection, ca. 1907-1927, AIS.2014.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Iron and steel workers -- Pennsylvania -- Midland (Beaver County); Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Lantern slides; Transportation; Business and Industry; Iron and steel workers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Railroads -- Photographs; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- History; New York (State); Colonial Steel Company
- Colonial Steel Company, ca. 1917-1927; I.; 24 items
  Scope and Content Notes
  The images in this series depict Colonial Steel Company from ca. 1917-1927. This series also includes a 1927 date book. The company was organized in 1901 and specialized in making hardened, tempered steel used to make tools. The company was absorbed by Vanadium Alloys Steel Company in 1928. The mill was located in Monaca, Pa., in Beaver County.
  - Colonial Steel Plant (Box 2, Slide 42)
  - Puddling (Box 2, Slide 43)
  - Tapping Slag in Puddle Furnace (Box 2, Slide 44)
  - Drawing Iron from Puddling Furnace (Box 2, Slide 45)
  - Puddled Ball of Iron Entering Squeezer in a Puddling Mill (Box 2, Slide 46)
  - Rolling Muck Bar (Box 2, Slide 47)
  - Rolling Bars 16" Mill (Box 2, Slide 48)
  - Rolling Bars 9" Mill (Box 2, Slide 49)
  - Rolling Bar 12" Mill (Box 2, Slide 50)
  - Shearing Muck Bar (Box 2, Slide 51)
  - Packing Crucibles (Box 2, Slide 52)
  - Drawing Crucibles from Furnace (Box 2, Slide 53)
  - Drawing Crucibles from Furnace 2 (Box 2, Slide 54)
  - Teaming Ingots from Crucible (Box 2, Slide 55)
  - Casting Crucible Ingots with Ladle (Box 2, Slide 56)
  - Stripping Ingots (Box 2, Slide 57)
  - Cogging Ingots on Big Hammer (Box 2, Slide 58)
  - Finishing Large Squares on Hammer (Box 2, Slide 59)
  - Reducing Billets (Box 2, Slide 60)
  - Forging on Hammer (Box 2, Slide 61)
  - Hammering on Tilt Hammer (Box 2, Slide 62)
  - Shipping from Warehouse (Box 2, Slide 63)
  - Inspection for Seams (Box 2, Slide 64)
  - Inspection Topping (Box 2, Slide 65)
  - Colonial Steel Datebook, 1927 (Box 2, Item 1)
- Steel Processes, Products, and Equipment, ca. 1907-1927; II.; 53 items
  This series contains images that show the different processes for making steel. These pictures were taken in Pennsylvania and New York. The dates for this series are unknown.
  - Charging Side Open Hearth Furnaces Charging Hot Metal (Box 1, Slide 3)
  - Carrie Blast Furnaces (Box 1, Slide 4)
  - Tapping Side Open Hearth Furnaces- Ladles in Position (Box 1, Slide 5)
  - 2BB and 122 Duquesne Blast Furnace (Box 1, Slide 6)
  - Duquesne Blast Furnace (Box 1, Slide 7)
  - Duquesne Works (?) (Box 1, Slide 8)
  - Duquesne Works (?) (Box 1, Slide 9)
  - Installation of Three Mesa Steam blowing Engines at the Plant of the McKinney Steel Company (Box 1, Slide 10)
  - Brown Hoist Unloaders (Box 1, Slide 11)
  - Bunkers and Transporter under Construction (Box 1, Slide 12)
  - Hewlett (Box 1, Slide 13)
  - Hewlett Machines (Box 1, Slide 14)
  - Plant of the Blast furnace (Box 1, Slide 15)
  - Filling Shell with Nitro-Glycerin, for Shooting Oil Well (Box 1, Slide 16)
  - Shooting Oil Well (Box 1, Slide 17)
  - Rabbler at Work at Puddling Furnace Rolling Mill, 1911 (Box 1, Slide 18)
  - Hydraulic Shears Cutting 5 Inch Steel Slabs, 1907 (Box 1, Slide 19)
  - Pouring Molten Steel into Ladle (Box 1, Slide 20)
  - Tapping an Open-Hearth Furnace (Box 1, Slide 21)
  - Coal Barges on the Monongahela (Box 1, Slide 22)
  - Plant of the Blast Furnace (Box 1, Slide 23)
  - Confluence of the Allegheny and Monongahela Rivers (Box 1, Slide 24)
  - Bessemer Converter in Action Blowing Iron into Steel (Box 1, Slide 25)
  - One Ton Herault Furnace, Front View before Tapping Heat (Box 1, Slide 26)
  - Steel Mills at Night (Box 1, Slide 27)
  - Drawing off Molten Iron from Blast Furnace to make "Pigs" (Box 1, Slide 28)
  - Drawing off Slag from Blast Furnace, 1910 (Box 1, Slide 29)
  - Molds being filled with Molten Iron (Box 1, Slide 30)
  - Erecting Shop (Box 1, Slide 31)
  - Furnaces (Box 1, Slide 32)
  - Filling Molds with Steel (Box 1, Slide 33)
  - Mountain Iron Mine (Box 1, Slide 34)
  - Press (Box 1, Slide 35)
  - The Huge Hot Blast Furnaces (Box 1, Slide 36)
  - Coining Presses Government Mint (Box 1, Slide 37)
  - Pouring Pig Iron into a 1,300 Ton Mixer (Box 1, Slide 38)
  - Blast Furnace (Box 1, Slide 39)
  - Jones and Laughlin Steel Co. (Box 1, Slide 40)
  - Coke Oven (Box 1, Slide 41)
  - Steel Laborers (Box 1, Slide 66)
  - U.S Steel Duquesne Works 22" Bar Mill (Box 1, Slide 67)
  - Blast Furnace/ Stove Diagram (Box 1, Slide 68)
  - Coal Yard (Box 1, Slide 69)
  - Steel Manufacturing (Box 1, Slide 70)
  - Slab (Box 1, Slide 71)
  - Largest Plate Mill in the - Lukens Steel Co. (Box 1, Slide 72)
  - Slab (Box 1, Slide 73)
  - Machined Steel (Box 1, Slide 74)
  - Sheet Roller (Box 1, Slide 75)
  - Nickel Shot and Ladle Diagram (Box 1, Slide 76)
  - Mill Buildings (Box 1, Slide 77)
  - Nickel Cast Iron in Large Rack Gear for Car Wheel Lathes (Box 1, Slide 78)
  - Driven Machine Equipment (Box 1, Slide 79)
- Topical, III.; 3 items
  The slides in this series primarily feature railroad scenes, including Pennsylvania Station in Pittsburgh, with the exception of one view of children gardening at a Philadelphia School. The dates for this series are unknown.
  - Ore Reclaiming Equipment (Box 1, Slide 1)
  - The Pennsylvania Station (Box 1, Slide 2)
  - School Gardens as a Practical Educational Method (Box 1, Slide 80)